Finding Aid for News and Information Services (University of Michigan) Audiovisual Materials
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Digital Video
  - News Briefs, 2007-2012
    - Local business leaders testify 2009, .mov file; The heads of three Michigan economic development organizations came to U-M to testify before the State Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Higher Education. They spoke on behalf of Michigan's University Research Corridor on May 15, 2009. (urcmich.org) State Senate hearing held at U-M Local business leaders testify before state senate.
    - Maiacetus: Mother whale 2009, .mov file; Two newly described fossil whales, a pregnant female and a male of the same species, reveal how primitive whales gave birth (on land) and provide new insights into how whales made the transition from land to sea. Fossil find reveals details of early whale evolution Interview and b-roll of Philip Gingerich with fossils, describing discovery and significance of the find.
    - Making a difference 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan College of Engineering students lead several initiatives for sustainable development in Jamaica through BLUElab project University of Michigan students lead projects in Jamaica. Interview with U-M students.
    - Michigan's student potential 2009, .mov file; On May 15 2009, students from the University of Michigan, Michigan State University and Wayne State University came to U-M to testify before the State Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Higher Education. They spoke on behalf of Michigan's University Research Corridor. (urcmich.org) Class of 2009 State Senate testimony.
    - Music moves microfluidic drops 2009, .mov file; This video provided by College of Engineering researchers demonstrates how sound waves can be used to move droplets through microfluidic devices. U-M researchers use music to move liquid in tiny experiments. Demonstration video.
    - Nanomovie 1 2009, .mov file; This movie shows an RNA molecule from the HIV genome (HIV-1 TAR) visualized at atomic resolution. HIV-1 TAR is a highly studied drug target. This animation represents the first time that experimentally validated, large-amplitude motions can be visualized at atomic scale. Laying groundwork for a new approach to drug design This movie shows an RNA molecule from the HIV genome (HIV-1 TAR) visualized at atomic resolution. HIV-1 TAR is a highly studied drug target. This animation represents the first time that experimentally validated, large-amplitude motions can be visualized at atomic scale.
    - Nanomovie 2 2009, .mov file; This movie provides new insights into the mechanics of RNA motion by showing how the shape of the HIV-1 TAR molecule changes when a connector linking two helices is shortened. Laying groundwork for a new approach to drug design This movie provides new insights into the mechanics of RNA motion by showing how the shape of the HIV-1 TAR molecule changes when a connector linking two helices is shortened.
    - New federal stem cell rules 2009, .mov file; Sean Morrison, director of the U-M Center for Stem Cell Biology, discusses the revised guidelines for federally funded embryonic stem cell research. Interview with Sean Morrison.
    - No child left behind 2009, .mov file; U-M professor Brian Jacob discusses his research findings on No Child Left Behind Act. The act produces mixed results on student achievement A video interview with Brian Jacob, professor of public policy and economics.
    - Out of the Blue 2009, .mov file; Highlights of the new addition/renovation at the University of Michigan Museum of Art. Out of the Blue segment on UMMA Highlights of the new addition/renovation at the University of Michigan Museum of Art.
    - Politics of health care reform 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan professor discusses the politics of the proposed health care reforms. Interview with professor Michael Traugott.
    - President Coleman at Rotary 2009, .mov file; President Coleman speaks about the U-M's commitment to keeping Ann Arbor vibrant, the University's physical growth and the U-M's continually growing research portfolio. U-M President Mary Sue Coleman at Ann Arbor Rotary Club President Coleman speaks about the U-M's commitment to keeping Ann Arbor vibrant, the University's physical growth and the U-M's continually growing research portfolio.
    - Reform at patient, doc level 2009, .mov file; U-M School of Public Health professor discusses changes that must happen at the patient and doctor level for reform to succeed Health reform requires patient-physician level change Video interview with Leon Wyszewianski.
    - Reinventing the automobile 2009, .mp4 file; General Motors and the University of Michigan have formed the GM/U-M Institute of Automotive Research and Education, with a strategic focus on reinventing the automobile and developing the next generation of high-efficiency vehicles powered by diverse energy sources. General Motors and U-M establish new institute. Video of press conference.
    - Remembering the Berlin Wall 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan professor remembers the Berlin Wall University of Michigan Professor remembers Interview with Prof Piotr Michalowski.
    - Restructuring General Motors 2009, .mov file; Professor Martin Zimmerman discusses GM's bankruptcy Expert on GM bankruptcy Interview with Business Professor Martin Zimmerman.
    - Running on empty 2009, .mov file; Car companies at the Detroit auto show are featuring electric vehicles and gasoline/electric hybrids. Electric vehicles are the big hit of the 2009 auto show. Video interview and b-roll with Bruce Belzowski.
    - Self-healing concrete 2009, .mov file; A concrete material developed at the University of Michigan can heal itself when it cracks. No human intervention is necessary---just water and carbon dioxide. A new material can mend itself when it cracks Video interview with professor Victor Li.
    - Student entrepreneurs 2009, .mov file; Neurophysiology for high school students. Crowdsourcing for product development. Socially-conscious t-shirts. These are three student business ideas getting started in Ann Arbor with help from the University of Michigan's Center for Entrepreneurship. The Center for Entrepreneurship helps student businesses Interviews with Thomas Zurbuchen, director of the Center for Entrepreneurship, plus interviews with founders of three student businesses: Crowd Clarity, Backyard Brains and The Bearon.
    - Student speaker Vikrum Vora 2009, .mov file; Literature, Science, and the Arts senior Vikrum Vora was student speaker at the University of Michigan 2009 winter commencement.
    - Student teams 2009, .mp4 file; The College of Engineering is placing a new emphasis on student teams, which offer hands-on learning that reinforces classroom teachings. Hands-on learning at Michigan Engineering. Video interviews with students and professors.
    - Sunny outlook 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan Solar Car Team showcase Infinium as they prepare for the World Solar Car Challenge in Australia. U-M Solar Car Team prepares for World Challenge. Interview with members of Solar Car Team.
    - Supreme Court vacancy 2009, .mov file; U-M law professor Richard Friedman discusses President Obama's pick to replace retiring Supreme Court justice David Souter. Battle looms over Obama's first nomination. Video interview with U-M Richard Friedman,
    - TechArb 2009, .mov file; With help from the U-M Center for Entrepreneurship and RPM Ventures, a group of students has started a small-business incubator in the basement of an Ann Arbor building. A business incubator founded by U-Michigan students. Video including interviews with students and professors involved in the incubator.
    - Testing in zero gravity 2009, .mov file; University of Michigan aerospace engineering students test NanoFET thrusters in zero gravity. U-M Students Test NanoFET. Interview with professor Alec Gallimore and students testing NanoFET technology.
    - The Burton Tower Carillon 2009, .mov file; The daily chiming of carillon bells in Burton Tower on Central Campus is a familiar sound at the University of Michigan. University Carillonneur Steven Ball. Video and interview with Steven Ball.
    - The impact of video games 2009, .mov file; New research shows that playing some video games makes children kinder and more likely to help -- not hurt -- other people. Playing can make children more likely to help others news video with professor Brad Bushman
    - The road to economic recovery 2009, .mov file; Professor Marina Whitman talks about what the newly approved stimulus package will mean to consumers Economic stimulus plan to give immediate relief to consumers. Video interview with Marina Whitman.
    - Tracing the vine of history 2009, .mov file; 500 Years of Winemaking in America offers an intriguing examination of how the pursuit of making memorable wine parallels the triumphs and travails of American history. Clements Library exhibit looks at 500 years of winemaking Exhibit curator Daniel Longone gives a brief tour of the compelling artifacts and books in the exhibit.
    - U-M launches stem cell center 2009, .mov file; This is a video from a March 9 news briefing announcing the creation of the U-M Consortium for Stem Cell Therapies. New consortium will create embryonic stem cell lines. Video featuring stem cell researchers Sean Morrison, Sue O'Shea and Gary Smith.
    - University of Michigan Automakers and the Feds 2009, .flv and .mp4 files; New vehicles should please the auto industry's newest stakeholder---the federal government.
    - University of Michigan Innovation economy partnership 2009, .flv and .mp4 files; V.P. for Research Stephen Forrest talks about U-M's commitment to transforming the economy of Michigan.
    - University of Michigan Reinventing the automobile 2009, .flv and .mp4 files; General Motors and U-M establish new institute.
    - University of Michigan Student teams 2009, .flv and .mp4 files; Hands-on learning at Michigan Engineering.
    - URC Presidents testimony 2009, .mov file; Presidents from the University of Michigan, Michigan State University and Wayne State University came to U-M to testify before the State Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Higher Education. They spoke on behalf of Michigan's University Research Corridor on May 15, 2009. (urcmich.org) State Senate hearing held at U-M, MSU and WSU presidents address the State Senate.
    - USA Learns 2009, .mov file; USA Learns.org has attracted more than half a million visits in less than 3 months, showing the power of distance learning to help immigrants learn English. A new web site helps immigrants learn English video interview with professors and students.
    - Wall Street in crisis 2009, .mov file; Wall Street was rocked this week as Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc. filed for bankruptcy, Merrill Lynch and Co. sold itself to Bank of America Corp. and insurer American International Group Inc. saw its shares plummet as it scrambled to raise billions to stay afloat. Ross Professor Amiyatosh Purnanandam explains how the investment banking world got to this point, and what the future holds for the industry, regulators and average Americans. Banking expert: How we got here and where we're headed? News video commentary with professor.
    - Aging in contemporary China 2010, .mov file; An ISR researcher is studying how Chinese families in the country and the city are coping with caring for aging family members. How rapid social change has affected growing old in China? Video slideshow narrated by researcher.
    - Americans live close to mothers 2010, .mov file; Interview with U-M economist Janice Compton about her findings that most Americans live close to their mothers. Interview with Janice Compton.
    - BioKIDS day out 2010, .mov file; U-M Ecology and Evolutionary Biology faculty and students plan a day out for Detroit Public Schools students who participated in BioKIDS. Visit to Henry Ford estate Interview with EEB faculty and DPS students.
    - Campus scenes 2010, .flv and .mp4 files; Various video clips of campus scenes; taken in preparation for Spring 2010 commencement. Includes the Michigan Union, Museum of Art, Angell hall, the Diag, Burton Tower and aerial shots.
    - Capping an oil leak 2010, .mov file; University of Michigan concluded a month long camp for high school students with an innovative competition - capping an oil leak. High school students compete at U-M interview with students and instructors.
    - Colossal Fossil 2010, .mov file; Learn about how new whale fossil was discovered and the process involved in getting it ready for exhibit and research. New whale exhibit at U-M museum Interview with Gingerich, Amy Harris, William Sanders, Mike Cherney, Daniel Erickson.
    - Confusion over health reform? 2010, .mov file; U-M School of Public Health Professor Leon Wyszewianski discusses some of the possible misconceptions about the new health care reform bill. Possible misconceptions about the health care reform bill. A brief interview with one subject about health care reform.
    - Creeping Crinoid 2010, .mp4 file; A crawling sea lily, Neocrinus decorus, off Grand Bahama Island at a depth of about 1200 feet. In its normal, living position, the finger-like appendages of the stalk attach the animal to the bottom, and elevated arms form a circular filter oriented perpendicular to the current. The stalk is about 2 feet long Sea lilies creep along ocean floor to escape hungry urchins. Short video clip of sea lily crawling along ocean floor.
    - Dramatic Truth 2010, .mov file; A short profile of Ralph Williams, who plays a pivotal role as a contributor and advisor during RSC residency Ralph Williams' legendary passion for teaching, Shakespeare. Williams discusses what motivates him as a teacher and scholar.
    - Drug regrows bone in gum disease 2010, .mov file; In a new study at School of Dentistry, researchers show benefits of using osteoporosis drug for periodontal patients. U-M researchers study show benefits for periodontal patients video with researcher, patient.
    - Electricity in our brains 2010, .mov file; Scientists are one step closer to limbs powered by electrical signals from the brain thanks to a new U-M study. New U-M study harnesses power of electricity in the brain interview with Dan Ferris, Joseph Gwin and b-roll.
    - Embryonic stem cell line 2010, .mov file; U-M scientists have created Michigan's first human embryonic stem cell line, achieving a long-sought goal that provides the foundation for future efforts to develop innovative disease treatments and cures. U-M create state's first human embryonic stem cell line The video will include an in-lab interview with stem cell scientist Gary Smith, as well as B-Roll of lab techs working with human embryonic stem cells. We will also include still microscope shots showing embryonic stem cells and cell colonies.
    - Epsilon Aurigae eclipse 2010, .mp4 file; Using an instrument created at the University of Michigan, astronomers have for the first time imaged a peculiar binary star eclipse that happens once every 27 years. Scientists capture a peculiar stellar eclipse Animation of epsilon Aurigae eclipse, 2009.
    - Fashion, power and politics 2010, .mov file; Robin Givhan talks about fashion, power and politics in Washington. U-M alumna talks about fashion in Washington circles podcast with images with Robin Givhan.
    - Getting up with the kids 2010, .mov file; Working mothers are still two and a half times as likely as working dads to get up at night to care for babies and small children. Working women are more likely to interrupt their sleep Interview with researcher, animated graphics, b-roll.
    - Happiness is rising around the world 2010, .flv and .mp4 files; ISR World Values Survey identifies happiest nations in the world.
    - Heart Walk May 15 2010, .mov file; U-M Chief Health Officer Robert Winfield and Wellness Coordinator Colleen Greene urge faculty, staff and students to walk or run for cardiac health. Campus urged to participate U-M Chief Health Officer Robert Winfield, Wellness Coordinator Colleen Greene discuss Health Walk and related activities.
    - Improving IVF pregnancy rates 2010, .mov file; University of Michigan professors have devised a new instrument that exposes developing embryos to motions similar to those that occur in the body, leading to higher in vitro fertilization pregnancy rates in mice. A new device mimics motions that occur in the body Interview with Gary Smith and Shu Takayama.
    - Inspiring tomorrow's engineers 2010, .mov file; At the Michigan Engineering Zone in Detroit, more than 100 high school students from across the city gather to build robots for the national FIRST Robotics competition. The U-M College of Engineering is sponsoring the zone in collaboration with Detroit Public Schools. Michigan Engineering helps Detroit students build robots Video interviews and footage of Detroit high school students building robots.
    - Justice in Cambodia 2010, .flv and .mp4 files; U-M professor John Ciorciari discusses UN tribunal's verdict in first case.
    - Microfluidic circuit 2010, .mp4 file; One circuit is serving as the clocking signal of another circuit so that the branching fluids switch in unison. Demonstration of integrated microfluidic circuit. Video of one circuit is serving as the clocking signal of another circuit so that the branching fluids switch in unison.
    - Midterm patterns and predictions 2010, .mov file; Veteran researcher Michael Traugott explains the factors behind midterm patterns and predicts 2010 outcomes. What the past tells us about midterm prospects. Video interview with expert plus animated graphics and images.
    - Minding the Gap 2010, .mov file; ISR researcher Philippa Clarke compares how well the U.S. and the U.K. are meeting the World Health Organization's vision for Age-Friendly Cities. Environments can enable, not disable Video slideshow with narration by Clarke.
    - Modern day slavery 2010, .flv and .mp4 files; The U-M Law School's Human Trafficking Clinic fights to stop modern slavery.
    - New programs at U-M 2010, .mov file; U-M President Mary Sue Coleman announce an agreement with Aaron Williams, Director of Peace Corps partnering 3 new international programs New International programs in partnership with Peace Corps signing press conference.
    - Parents seek Internet safety 2010, .mov file; Parents are taking action to safeguard their children from cyberbullying. Parents take steps to protect kids from cyberbullying A video interview with Matthew Davis about parents becoming increasingly concerned about bullying and cyberbullying.
    - Patients and medical decisions 2010, .mov file; New study looks at how patients approach medical decision making. New study by U-M researcher looks at medical decision making Interview with Brian Zikmund-Fisher.
    - Physics of Hockey 2010, .mov file; University of Michigan Physics Department Chair Brad Orr demonstrates how physics is at the core of checking, shooting and skating in ice hockey, the world's fastest sport. Orr will give a full public lecture on the physics of hockey with demonstrations at 1:30 p.m. on Dec. 11. Details at http://ns.umich.edu/htdocs/releases/story.php?id=8162. Physics is at the heart of the game. Video of Physics chat.
    - Playing Along 2010, .mov file; Acclaimed theatre company brings playwrights, actors, directors to reconstruct lost Shakespeare play Royal Shakespeare Co. and U-M creating three new plays Ralph Williams presents an overview of residency promising to recast U-M's role as collaborator in creative process.
    - Politics and longevity 2010, .mov file; ISR researcher Jose Tapia Granados discusses his new study Aren't democracies better for health than dictatorships? Interview with research scientist.
    - RAX in space 2010, .mov file; Aerospace and computer engineering students take lead roles as they get ready to launch first NSF space mission- radio aurora explorer- RAX. U-M students part of space mission interviews with aerospace faculty and students.
    - Risky business 2010, .mp4 file; Sean Morrison, director of the U-M Center for Stem Cell Biology, discusses the risky treatments offered by unregulated foreign stem cell clinics. Sean Morrison discusses foreign stem cell clinics Interview. To be posted on the U-M stem cell research home page (www.umich.edu/stemcell)by John Pariseau.
    - Saadanius hijazensis fossil 2010, .flv and .mp4 files; The new fossil catarrhine, Saadanius hijazensis, dates from 29 million to 28 million years ago and lacks the specialized features that distinguish modern apes and Old World monkeys, suggesting that the split had not yet occurred. The researchers' analysis of the fossil leads them to believe its physical features are much like those of the last common ancestor of Old World monkeys and apes.
    - Shopping behavior copy evolution 2010, .mov file; U-M researcher Daniel Kruger explains the different shopping styles with evolution theory. Interview with Daniel Kruger.
    - Snakes and sauropods 2010, .mov file; The remains of an extraordinary fossil unearthed in 67-million-year-old sediments from Gujarat, western India reveal that snakes preyed on hatchling dinosaurs. Ancient snake fed on baby dinosaurs Interview with paleontologist Jeff Wilson, showing a 3-D sculpture of the vignette that the fossil represents.
    - Social Venture Creation 2010, .mov file; U-M students talk about their projects and the social venture creation class. A University of Michigan class HD video of social venture creation class.
    - Spill's long lasting effects 2010, .mov file; Expert video of U-M Law Professor David Uhlmann U-M Expert on BP Oil Spill and its consequences Interview with David Uhlmann.
    - Sports as economic development 2010, .mov file; U-M professor Mark Rosentraub discusses the impact of sports development on Detroit. Detroit - a failed venture? Interview with Mark Rosentraub.
    - State of American orchestras 2010, .mov file; In January, 2010, a landmark conference concerning the American orchestra was held at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, examining the wide-reaching cultural impact that the orchestra has had in America, and exploring how orchestras and academia might partner effectively to extend this impact. Several of the conference participants were interviewed for this video. At a crossroad On January, 2010, a landmark conference concerning the American orchestra was held at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, examining the wide-reaching cultural impact that the orchestra has had in America, and exploring how orchestras and academia might partner effectively to extend this impact.
    - Sustainable mobility 2010, .mov file; Automakers at the 2010 North American International Auto Show have big hopes for their new small vehicles---hipper, more fuel-efficient, environmentally sound cars. Small cars making big waves at Detroit auto show Video of researcher discussing new vehicles with b-roll of cars.
    - The biological roots of PTSD 2010, .mov file; University of Michigan researchers and their colleagues say they've identified what appears to be a crucial step in the chain of biological events leading to post-traumatic stress disorder. U-M researchers identify crucial step. Interview with Monica Uddin about her new study.
    - The last card 2010, .mov file; 108 cases will be removed from the University of Michigan Hatcher Graduate Library. More than 6.1 million volumes are listed in the catalogs. Removing the card catalogs from U-M libraries 108 cases will be removed from the University of Michigan Hatcher Graduate Library. More than 6.1 million volumes are listed in the catalogs.